Mary Jeffries Bruce and the Sunday Evening Forum collection, 1942-1993
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
- Series I: Albums, 1942-1976
  - Album 13, 1963-1964 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    1963-1964 Season. Prince Hubertus zu Loewenstien former member of the German Parliament and special advisor to the German Federal Government Information Office spoke to the forum on the topic of “The Federal Republic of Germany looks at the Nuclear Test Ban Treaty”. Oregon Governor Mark Hatfield discussed the topic “Opportunity versus Importunity”. Phillip Cummings, a news analyst lectured on “The Emerging Countries in Africa and Asia”. Congressman James Roosevelt from California addressed the forum on “Civil Rights and Liberties in 1963”. General Lauris Norstad, Supreme Allied Commander in Europe and Commander-Chief of U.S. European Forces from 1956-1963, discussed “NATO, Past and Present.” Curtis Nagel returned for his 10th appearance and presented a film entitled “Portraits of Scandinavia”. Martin Agronsky a news analyst discussed “the United States in a Changing World.” Television film producer, Eric Pavel narrated his film “The Alpine World’. The 1963-1964 season closed with a film by Clifford Karmen entitle “The Union (Republic) of South Africa. The film covers the major geographical areas, principle industries, native life, and unique game reserves of Africa.
  - Loose items, 1963-1964 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Album 14, 1964-1965 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    1964-1965 Season was opened by Stan Midgely who presented a colored travel film called “Adventure in the Northwest”. Harlem Cleveland, assistant secretary of state for United Nations affairs spoke to the forum on the topic “The United Nations Today”. Drew Pearson a well-known Washington reporter spoke on “The Election’s Aftermath—Forecast for the Future”. Dr. Dale Liechty narrated a film about the hospital ship the SS Hope. Walter Cronkite famous television newscaster addressed the forum on the topic “LBJ and the World”. Abigail Van Buren (Dear Abbey) made her second appearance at the forum. John Goddard, television star of “This Exciting World,” narrated his film on “Adventure in the Far East”. Dean Burch, retiring chairman of the Republican Party, spoke on the past presidential election or “What Happen in 1964”. Robert Davis presented a travelogue on Belgium. Eric Pavel narrated a film entitled “Six Gateways to the Caribbean”. The 1964-1965 forum closed with a performance by the Rincon High School Chorus and a film called “The Valley of the Rhine” narrated by Clifford Kamen.
  - Loose items, 1964-1965 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Album 15, 1965-1966 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    1965-1966 Season began with Stan Medgley narrating his “chucklelogue” film on Yellowstone, Grand Teton and Glacier National parks. Phillip Cummings, news analyst and economic consultant, made his 6th appearance at the Sunday Night Forum. His topic was “American Business Abroad: A Contribution to Peace or A problem to Diplomacy”. W. Averell Harriman U.S. Ambassador-at-large spoke on “The Challenges to Freedom and Peace”. Dr. J. Gerald Hooper narrated his new film “Only in Portugal”. Senator Paul Fannin from Arizona lectured on the topic “Washington – As I See It”. Representative Ogden Reid from New York and former ambassador to Israel spoke on “Can Congress be more effective in Foreign Policy?” Senator Jacob K. Javits from New York lectured on “Foreign Policy and Bipartisanship”. Dr. Murray Banks, a clinical psychologist and humorist spoke on “Live, Love and Laugh”. Dr. James Robinson presented a lecture and film on “Operation Crossroads”. Rev. Dr. Robinson founded a summer student study and work camp program in which 250 students worked on various projects throughout Africa. Karl Robinson narrated his award winning film “Hong Kong” showing the diversity and intensity of the country. The final program of the season featured the Liberty Singers, a group of University of Arizona folk singers.
  - Loose items, 1965-1966 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Album 16, 1966-1967 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    1966-67 Season marked the 25th anniversary for the Sunday Night forum. The season opened with Don Shaw who presented the film “Kingless Kingdom of Cambodia”. Bill Mauldin a two-time Pulitzer Prize winter and editorial cartoonist gave an illustrated lecture. Dr. Ralph J. Bunch, Undersecretary of the United Nations addressed the Sunday Night Forum on the topic “A Hard Look at the United Nations: Its current Crisis and Prospects”. Dr. Margaret Mead, renowned anthropologist, topic was “Ourselves as Others See Us”. Captain Irving Johnson narrated his latest film “Yankee Sails the Nile”. Representative Morris K. Udall from Arizona spoke on the subject “Issues facing the 90th Congress”. Curtis Nagel returned for his 13th appearance at the forum. He narrated his latest travelogue “Portraits of Mexico”. Gerald Ford, Republication Minority Leader from Michigan spoke on the topic “Our Republic – A review and Preview”. Bishop James A. Pike, former bishop of the Episcopal Diocese of California, lectured on the “Conflict Between Science and Religion”. David Brinkley spoke to the Forum about international communism. John Morley, a syndicated columnist who had just completed around-the-world trip spoke on the topic “I Saw Today’s Headline World”: Jose Molina and his company of Bailes Espanoles performed for the 25th Annual Patron Recognition Night.
  - Loose items, 1966-1967 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Album 17, 1967-1969 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    1967-1969 Season was launched with Jens Bjerre, a Danish film producer. He narrated his graphic film called “Red China” which lifted the Bamboo Curtain and portrayed Mao Tse-tungs Red China. Philip Cummings, economic consultant and news analyst discussed “The American Commitment: Is It Too Great?”. Arizona Representative Morris K. Udall declared that he had changed his mind on the Vietnam war and advocated the “de-escalation and de--Americanization of the war”. U.S. Representative John J. Rhodes spoke on the “Evolving Political Patterns of the late 20th century. Art Buchwald syndication humor columnist discussed his view on life as a “Son of the Great Society”. The Branko Krsmanovic Chorus of 80 voices from Yugoslavia performed for the Annual Patron Recognition Night. Harry Golden humorist and author lectured on “Only in America”, in which he attacked the primary problems facing America. Former Tucsonan Peter Grose, Washington correspondent for the New York Times spoke on the topic “Changes in the Soviet Union and how they affect the United States and our future relations”. Eric Sevareid a CBS television correspondent spoke to the forum and called President’s Johnson decision not to seek re-election a possible political tragedy. Eric Pavel once again presented the final session of the season with narration of his film “Florence and the Heart of Italy”.
    1968-1969 Season began with a film entitled “Bavaria, The Best of Southern Germany” narrated by Clay Francisco. Former Tucsonan Larry C. Mcquade, assistant secretary of commerce for domestic and international business addressed the forum on the topic on “The U.S. Dollar at Home and Abroad”. Arizona Representative Morris K. Udall returned to address the forum on the subject “The Meaning of the 1968 Elections”. Senator Mark Hatfield spoke on “Who Won? In the 1968 elections”. United States Attorney General Ramsey Clark told Tucsonans that “Poverty spawns crime and crime can be cured if American cared enough to remedy its root causes”: Burch Mann’s Ballet America performed “Big Country” performed at the Annual Patron Recognition Night. David Brinkley appeared for his third engagement of the Saturday Night Forum. He had just finished his 12th season of the Huntley – Brinkley Report and his topic was “Late Line News”. The forum presented a two member panel which discussed the “The Role of Government in Medical Care”. The discussion members were Edward R. Annis, MD, past president of the American Medical Association and Rashi Fein, Ph.D., professor of economics of medicine at Harvard University. Mrs. Martin Luther King, Jr. (Coretta Scott King) addressed the forum on the topic “The Individual’s Role in Today’s Turbulent World”.
  - Loose items, 1967-1969 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Album 18, 1969-1971 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    1969-1970 Season was opened with Lisa Hobbs, foreign correspondent who spoke on the topic “Red China Report”. U.S. Representative Rogers C. B. Morton from Maryland and secretary of the National Republican Congressional Committee spoke to the forum on the topic “The Republican Party meets the Challenges of the 70s”. Representative Morris K. Udall of Arizona lectured on “A Scenario for the 70’s”. Dr. S.I. Hayakawa, president of riot torn San Francisco State College addressed the forum on the topic of “ An Assessment of the Campus Scene”. Paul Harvey, news commentator gave the forum his opinions of the ills and wonders of the United States and it role in international politics. Up With People, a group of young musician, singers and dancers, performed at the Patron’s Recognition Night of the Sun Evening Forum. Mike Wallace, CBS news correspondent and on-the-air editor of the TV series 60 Minutes addressed the forum on the topic “The Press – Credible or Incredible?”.
    1970-1971 Season was opened with John Goddard, who returned for his 8th appearance, narrated his new documentary film “Exploring African Wonderlands”. Galo Plaza, secretary-general of the Organization of American States (OAS), addressed the forum on “The Organization of American States in the 1970’s”. Ralph Nader, Head of the Center for Study of Responsive Law, spoke on” Consumer Protection”. Native Arizona Richard Kleindienst, Deputy Attorney General to the United States spoke on “The Department of Justice Today – A Progress Report”. Park T. Hart, president of the Middle East Institute and former Ambassador to Turkey, Saudi Arabia, Kingdom of Kuwait and Jordan, spoke on “An American Policy of the Middle East. U.S. Senator Robert Packwood from Oregon lectured on the topic “Sex and Survival”. Ballet America appeared for the 2nd time at the Annual Patron Recognition Night. Howard K. Smith ABC television newsman reported on “The Changing Challenge to America”. Mayor Carl B. Stokes of Cleveland, the first African American to be elected to head a major city, spoke to the forum and spelled out his program for the survival of America’s cities. Representative Martha Griffiths from Michigan lectured on “Equal Rights for Women”. Eric Pavel closed out the 1970-71 season with his documentary film “Spain”.
  - Loose items, 1969-1971 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Album 19, 1971-1973 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    1971-1972 Season opened with William Moore who presented his color documentary film “Portraits of Australia”. John McCook Roots, foreign correspondent, spoke on the topic “China and the World Community – What Next?”. Kansas Senator Robert J. Dole the Republican National Chairman predicted a Richard Nixon-Hubert Humphrey rematch in the 1972 presidential election. Hjordis Kittel Park presented her documentary film the “Norse Adventure”. John W. Gardener, Chairman of Common Case told the forum that organized citizen action was the best way to rehabilitate America’s political and government institutions. Up With People performed for a second time at the Annual Patron Recognition Night. Jackie Robinson, the first African American player in major league baseball and a vice president of the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP) spoke to forum on the topic “The Challenge of the Seventies”. Ambassador George Bush permanent representative of the U.S. to the United Nations, spoke on “A Critical Look at the U.N.”. ABC news reporter Harry Reasoner spoke about President Nixon’s trip the Red China. The final presenter of the 1971-72 was Russ Potter who narrated his color film “High Himalaya”.
    1972-1973 Season opened with Gene Wiancko narrating his film “Yugoslavia and the Slavic Race”. John McCook Roots, foreign correspondent, reported on his recent trip to China and his meeting with Premier Chou En-lai. Norman Cousin, editor and founder of the magazine “World” gave an address entitled “World Report”, he emphasized that the biggest task world nations have is to build the strength of the United Nations. Dewitt Jones presented a film documentary on the Sierra Mountain Range and the founder of the Sierra Club, John Muir. Executive Director of the United Negro Fund and former Assistant Secretary in the Department of Labor spoke on the topic “Post Elections – Where Do We Go From Here?” Dick Reddy, journalist and producer of motion pictures, narrated his film “Mark Twain in Switzerland”. Huge Downs, former host of the NBC “Today Show” gave a speech on “The Media and the Ecological Crisis”. The Folk Ensemble from Yugoslavia called Radost was presented at the Annual Patron Recognition Night. Daniel Brown, director Office of Policy and Plans, Bureau of Public Affairs, Department of State, spoke on the “United States and Problems of the Middle East”. The Forum presented a Mexican Fiesta co-sponsored with the Tucson Festival Society, the program featured Los Payadores de Pueblo and Grupo Folkloric de Pima College. Harry Pederson, underwater photographer narrated his film “The Village Beneath the Sea” in the final program of the season.
  - Loose items, 1971-1973 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Album 20, 1973-1974 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    1973-1974 Season opened with Chris Borden, producer of documentary films and graduate of the University of Arizona, narrated his film “Micronesia-America’s Pacific Paradise”. John McCook Roots spoke about his visit to the Middle East and his talks with Israeli Prime Minister Golda Meir and Egyptian Foreign Minister El Zayyat. Congressman Morris K. Udall and economist Dr. Charles Walker, former deputy Treasury Secretary, debated “Tax Reform – What’s a Loophole?”. Maynard H. Jackson, newly elected mayor of Atlanta, Georgia, spoke on his policies and future plans for Atlanta. Hjordis Kittel Parker presented her documentary film “Scandinavian Medley”. John Chancellor, reporter for the NBC Nightly News, spoke on Watergate. Walter S. Dodson, Curtis Nagel, Thayer Soule, and Eric Pavel presented their films on Israel, the Rhine, Kenya, and England respectively.
  - Loose items, 1973-1974 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Album 21, 1974-1975, 1975-1976 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    The 1974-1975 Season opened with Scandinavian photographer Ed Lark presenting his documentary film “Norway”. Elliot Richardson, former U.S. Attorney General for the Nixon Administration spoke on the topic “New Politics”. Ken Wolfgang, producer of educational, industrial and historical films, narrated he documentary “In Search of Singapore”: House Minority Leader John J. Rhodes Republican from Arizona, spoke about the national political atmosphere following the Watergate scandal. Stan Midgley narrated his film “California”. Simcha Dintz, Israel’s ambassador to the United States, spoke on the U.S. – Arab arms deal. Humorist Don Cooper, narrated his film documentary “Lumberjack in Alaska”. Thayer Soule, film-lecturer, presented his film “I Love Mexico”. Dr. Martin Luther King Sr., minister and father of the late Dr. Martin Luther King Jr., spoke at the forum on the subject “A Misplaced Emphasis”. The Hungarian Folk Ballet and the Gypsy Orchestra performed for the annual Patron Recognition Night. Howard K. Smith, co-anchorman on the “ABC Evening News”, topic was the “Changing Challenge to America”. Arthur Twomey, director of the Carnegie Institute narrated his film “Asiatic U.S.S.R. and Outer Mongolia. Robin Williams, film-lecturer, narrated his film “Life of Rome”, it was the last presentation of the 1974-75 season.
    The 1975-1976 Season opened with John Goddard, explorer and adventurer, he presented his film “Exploring Asian Wonderlands. Chris Borden narrated his documentary film “Iran – The Persia of Old”. Julian Bond, a Georgia State Senator and African American political leader, spoke to the forum on the subject “Apotheosis of the New Politics”. Jonathan Hagar, journalist and film-lecturer, narrated his film “Central America”. Senator James L. Buckley from New York spoke on federalism in the federal government. Robin Williams, University of Arizona graduate, presented a slide show entitle “Greek Island Odyssey”. The Sunday Evening Forum presented a special Bicentennial musical program entitled “In Harmony with Freedom” staring Norman Atkins and Judith McCauley. Added to the evenings program was a final farewell tribute to Ms. Mary Jefferies Bruce. Stan Migley presented the travel film “Colorado – The Centennial State”. David Brinkley, NBC newsman, spoke at the forum and predicted Gerald Ford would win the Presidential Election. The American International Folk Ballet performed for the Annual Patron Recognition Program: “Arizona Adventure” a documentary film was present by Robert Davis. Another Bicentennial program was presented “The Indian Cultural Heritage” in music and dance. The program included a tribute Ms. Mary Jeffries Bruce, who retired as director of the Forum following the night’s performance: Ken Wolfgang presented his documentary film “Ageless India”.
  - Loose items, 1974-1974, 1975-1976 (Box 9, Folder 6)
- Series II Retirement booklet, 1976
  - Retirement booklet (Box 9, Folder 7)
    A bound collection of letters written by former guests of the Sunday Night Forum given to Ms. Mary Jefferies Bruce upon her retirement by the Board of Directors of the Sunday Night Forum and signed by the Chairman, Rev. Stanley C. Brown.
- Series III Oleg Kirillov materials, 1960-1993
  Contains materials collected by Oleg Kirillov, who met Mary Jeffries Bruce via a bookstore in St. Petersburg and developed a lasting friendship. Bruce refers to herself as Kirillov’s aunt in correspondence. Series includes correspondence, clippings and photographs.
  - Correspondence from Mary Jeffries Bruce to Oleg Kirillov and family, 1963-1993 (Box 10, Folder 1-3)
  - The Sunday Evening Forum, Preview of Programs, 1962-1975 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Pamphlets and ephemera, 1960, 1963, 1972 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Clippings, 1958-1989 (Box 10, Folder 6-7)
  - Photographs, portraits of Bruce and family, 1976-1980 (Box 10, Folder 8)